Finding Aid for Yale Kamisar Papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Research Topical Files, 1962-1981
  - S-W
    - Vining, G. Joseph (Prof.), 1969 (Box 28)
    - Vodnoy, Joseph T., 1968 (Box 28)
    - Volkmann-Schulck, Thomas, 1978 (Box 28)
    - Von Moschzisker, Michael, 1965 (Box 28)
    - Vorenberg, James (Prof.), 1965-1968; 1970-1971; 1973-1974 (Box 28)
    - Wachtler, Sol, 1975; 1980 (Box 28)
    - Waggoner, M. (Box 28)
    - Walker, Dennis P. III, 1972-1973 (Box 28)
    - Wallace, Bruce, 1972 (Box 28)
    - Walsh, William F., 1967-1968 (Box 28)
    - Walters, Robert, 1965 (Box 28)
    - Wanger, Eugene (Box 28)
    - Ware, Mitchell, 1972 (Box 28)
    - Warren, Earl (Chief Justice), 1967; 1969 (Box 28)
    - Warren, William, 1977 (Box 28)
    - Warshal, Rabbi Bruce S., 1970; 1972 (Box 28)
    - Wasserstrom, Silas, 1967 (Box 28)
    - Waterman, Sterry R., Jr., 1966 (Box 28)
    - Watson, Andrew, 1972 (Box 28)
    - Watts, L. Poindexter, 1966 (Box 28)
    - Webber, Howard R., 1969 (Box 28)
    - Wechsler, E.M. (Box 28)
    - Wechsler, Herbert, 1965-1966; 1968-1969; 1973 (Box 28)
    - Wechsler, James (The New York Post), 1968 (Box 28)
    - Weeden, Richard, 1976 (Box 28)
    - Weeks, John A., 1966 (Box 28)
    - Weinberg, Larry P. (Box 28)
    - Weiner, William, 1970 (Box 28)
    - Weinfeld, Edward (Hon.), 1966; 1977; 1979 (Box 28)
    - Weinreb, Criminal Process, 1974 (Box 28)
    - West Publishing Company, 1968-1969 (Box 28)
    - Whitman, Christina, 1974 (Box 28)
- Speech, Debate, Lecture, and Presentation Files
  The Speech, Debate, Lecture, and Presentation series (1.3 linear feet), documenting the period from 1963 to 1994, is a partial file of the many speeches that Kamisar gave on capital punishment, constitutional freedoms such as the Fourth Amendment exclusionary rule and the Miranda right to remain silent, criminal justice, the right-to-die, and various Supreme Court decisions. The speeches are arranged chronologically, with undated speeches filed first. The Law Week Conference presentations (1983-1994), sponsored by the Bureau of National Affairs, are filed together at the end of the Speeches series. These are usually commentaries on notable cases in the past year.
  - "The 'Credibility Gap' in the U.S. Attorney General's Office,", undated (Box 15)
  - Miranda (Fordham University), undated (Box 15)
  - Miranda (Military Court), undated (Box 15)
  - "Resolved: The U.S. Supreme Court has Set Unrealistic and Inflexible Standards for Criminal Prosecution" (Oberlin College), undated (Box 15)
  - "United States v. Salerno,", undated (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches, 1959; undated (Box 15)
  - "The Police Chief, the College Coach and the Problem of 'Absentee Management'...and Other Reflections on the Tactics of 'Police-Prosecution' minded critics of the Courts," (American Psychological Association), 1963 (Box 15)
  - Proceedings (Third Circuit Judicial Conference), 1965 (Box 15)
  - Criminal Law Conference (NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, Inc.), 1966 (Box 15)
  - " Miranda v. Arizona: Some Comments on the Old 'New' Fifth Amendment" (National Conference on Police Interrogation and Confessions, Institute of Continuing Legal Education and Practicing Law Institute), 1966 (Box 15)
  - "The Question in Historical and Practical Perspective" (Criminal Law Section, American Bar Association), 1967 (Box 15)
  - "The Federal Supreme Court and the Enhancement of Justice" (Michigan State Conference of NAACP Branches Annual Convention), 1967 (Box 15)
  - "Why Talk About Supreme Court Decisions 'Encourage' Criminals Only Encourages a False View of the Real Problem" (New York University School of Law), 1967 (Box 15)
  - Stop and Frisk Cases (Committee on Supreme Court Decisions, Association of American Law Schools), 1967 (Box 15)
  - Remarks (Philadelphia Bar Association Annual Bench-Bar Conference), 1969 (Box 15)
  - "Capital Punishment" (Round Table Meeting, San Francisco), 1969 (Box 15)
  - "The Burger Court Slides Down the Mountain" (Kenneth J. Hodson Lecture in Criminal Law, Judge Advocate General's School, Charlottesville, VA), 1973 (Box 15)
  - "Current Developments and Trends in Criminal Procedure,", 1974; 1975 (Box 15)
  - "Criminal Procedure and the Waves of History (Judicial Conference of the Third Circuit of the United States), 1976 (Box 15)
  - "A Life Not (or no Longer) Worth Living: Are We Deciding the Issue Without Facing It?" (Mitchell Lecture, State University of New York, Buffalo), 1977 (Box 15)
  - "How We Got the Fourth Amendment Exclusionary Rule and Why We Need It" (U.S. Senate Judiciary Subcommittee on Criminal Law), 1982 (Box 15)
  - "Current Proposals to Improve, Cripple or Repeal the Exclusionary Rule" (University of Iowa Law School), 1982 (Box 15)
  - "Attacking Miranda's 'Bright Lines the Way Hounds Attack Foxes" (David C. Baum Memorial Lecture on Civil Rights and Liberties, University of Illinois), 1984 (Box 16)
  - "The Burger and Warren Courts and Constitutional-Criminal Procedure" (University of Michigan Law Alumni of Chicago), 1984 (Box 16)
  - Speech in Washington, 1984 (Box 16)
  - "The Tyranny of Small Decisions: The Decline and (Fall?) of the Warren Courts Great Due Process Cases" (Edward Douglass While Lectures on Citizenship, Louisiana State University), 1985 (Box 16)
  - "Some Call it 'Death with Dignity,' Others Call it the 'Right to Die.' What is it Really?" (Philip A. Hart Lecture, Georgetown University Law Center), 1988 (Box 16)
  - "What is 'Search' and 'Seizure?" (University of Minnesota Law School), 1988 (Box 16)
  - "'Freedom's Words' and 'Contested Instances': The Fourth Amendment and Its Exclusionary Rule,", 1991 (Box 16)
  - "The Fourth Amendment and Its Exclusionary Rule" (Bicentennial of the U.S. Bill of Rights Celebration), 1991 (Box 16)
  - "Death and Dying: Assisted Suicide and Active Euthanasia Move to Center Stage,", 1992 (Box 16)
  - Law Week Conferences
    - Fifth Annual Supreme Court Review and Constitutional Law Symposium, 1983 (Box 16)
    - "The Court's Growing Hostility to the Exclusionary Rule: Leon, Sheppard and Lopez-Mendoza,", 1984 (Box 16)
    - The Future of Miranda and the Fourth Amendment Exclusionary Rule, 1986 (Box 16)
    - "Police Interrogation and Confessions,", 1987 (Box 16)
    - Presentations, 1988; 1 folders
      - "Arrest, Search and Seizure" (Box 16)
      - "Police Interrogation and Confessions: Self-Incrimination and the Production of Documents" (Part II) (Box 16)
    - Presentations, 1989; 1 folders
      - "The Right to Confront Adverse Witnesses Face-to-Face: The Right to Counsel of One's Choice and the Execution of Juveniles and the Mentally Retarded" (Part III) (Box 16)
      - "The Drug Testing Cases" (Part I) (Box 16)
      - "The Right to Counsel" (Part III) (Box 16)
      - "The Death Penalty Cases" (Part IV) (Box 16)
    - "The 'Right to Die' Case: Cruzan v. Director, Missouri Dept. of Health,", 1990 (Box 16)
    - Presentations, 1991; 1 folders
      - "Arrest, Search and Seizure: Florida v. Bostick, California v. Hodari D. and California v. Acevedo" (Box 16)
      - "Confessions: Minnick v. Mississippi, McNeil v. Wisconsin" (Box 16)
    - Presentations, 1992; 1 folders
      - Georgia v. McCollum, Morgan v. Illinois, U.S. v. Jacobson, U.S. v. Alvarez-Machain, Riggins v. Nevada (Box 16)
      - Medina v. California, White v.Illinois, Hudson v. McMillian, U.S. v. Williams, Doggett v. U.S. (Box 16)
    - Presentations, 1993; 1 folders
      - Withrow v. Williams and Brecht v. Abrahamson (Part I) (Box 16)
      - Brecht v. Abrahamson (continued) Herrera v. Collins, U.S. v. Dunnigan, U.S. v. Jones, Minnesota v. Dickerson, Soldad v. Cook County (Part II) (Box 16)
      - U.S. v. Dixon, Lockhart v. Fretwell, Godinex v. Moran, Sullivan v. Louisiana (Part III (Box 16)
    - Presentations, 1994
      - "Peremptory Challenges Based on Gender: Proof Beyond a 'Reasonable Doubt" (Box 16)
      - "Police Interrogation and Confessions: Davis v. U.S. and Stansbury v. California" (Box 16)
  - Graduation Remarks, 1978-1998 (Box 16)
  - Programs for Speeches given, 1971; 1991-2000 (Box 16)
  - General, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Kentucky Speech, 1965 (Box 28)
- Teaching Files, 1959-2000; 7.6 linear feet
  The Teaching Files series (7.6 linear feet), covers 1959 to 2000 and includes assignments, cases, clippings, examinations and answers, notes, and occasional syllabi from Kamisar's classes in Constitutional Criminal Procedure (taught at Harvard University's Law School, 1964-1965), Constitutional Law (1971-1992), Criminal Justice (1977-1998), Criminal Law (taught at both the University of Minnesota and University of Michigan Law Schools, 1959-1997), and undated notes and cases for Criminal Proceedings.
  The largest subseries in the Teaching Files series is Criminal Law (6.7 linear feet). The Topical Teaching File is an alphabetical list of pertinent topics used in his teaching. These include Assisted Suicide, in particular folders on Jack Kevorkian and a 1993-1994 report from the Michigan Commission on Death and Dying; the Death Penalty, which contains the undated "Case of the Speluncian Explorers;" Euthanasia, with several folders on Jack Kevorkian and Karen Ann Quinlan, a 1997 transcript of the conference Socially-Assisted Dying: Media, Money & Meaning; and Mercy-Killing Legislation. Researchers will also find multiple folders on Evidence, the Exclusionary Rule, Felony Murder, Insanity Miranda v. Arizona, Necessity, and the Race Riots of 1967 in Detroit and Newark, New Jersey.
  Also included in this series are two VHS videocassettes. The first is Kamisar's Criminal Law Miranda v. Arizona lecture. The second is his last Criminal Law lecture given at the University of Michigan Law School, in December 2003.
  - Comparative Criminal Justice, undated (Box 16)
  - Constitutional Criminal Procedure
    - undated (Box 16)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 16)
  - Constitutional Criminal Procedure IV, [1964-1965] (Box 17)
  - Constitutional Law
    - First Amendment
      - Exams (Includes Answers), 1971-1993; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Exams (Future), 1981-1984 (Box 17)
      - General
        - 1984 (Box 17)
        - 1992 (Box 17)
      - Syllabus, 1982-1987; undated (Box 17)
    - General, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Criminal Justice
    - Assignments, 1981-1998 (Box 17)
    - Exam Answers, 1977-1987; undated (Box 17)
    - Exams, 1977-1999; undated; 3 folders (Box 17)
    - General, 1989-1992 (Box 17)
  - Criminal Law
    - undated, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - I, undated; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - II, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
    - III, undated (Box 17)
    - Introduction, 1964-1965 (Box 18)
    - 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - 1967-1973, 4 folders (Box 18)
    - 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - 1990, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Winter 1994 (Box 18)
    - 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Winter 1995, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 19)
      (Includes Cameras in Courtrooms)
    - Assignments, 1985-1988; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Examinations
      - Answers, 1966-1986 (Box 19)
      - Questions, 1966-1997; undated; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Questions (Not Used), 1997 (Box 19)
      - Syllabus, 1988 (Box 19)
    - Topical Teaching File
      - Assisted Suicide
        - 1994-1995 (Box 19)
        - Kevorkian, Jack, 1996; 1998-1999; 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Michigan Commission on Death and Dying, 1993-1994 (Box 19)
      - Capital Punishment, 1969; undated (Box 19)
      - Confessions, undated (Box 19)
      - Conspiracy Attempts, undated (Box 19)
      - Crime Crises, 1983 (Box 19)
      - Criminal Responsibility, undated (Box 20)
      - Deadly Force, 1965-1972; undated (Box 20)
      - Death Penalty
        - 1986, undated (Box 20)
        - Fall 1989 (Box 20)
        - Winter 1994 (Box 20)
        - 1995 (Box 20)
        - Case of the Speluncian Explorers, undated (Box 20)
        - Jurisprudence of Death, 1987 (Box 20)
      - Euthanasia
        - 1976-1977, 1988; 1997; undated; 6 folders (Box 20)
        - Alaska, 1999 (Box 20)
        - Articles, 1996-1999 (Box 20)
        - Clippings, 1967-1977 (Box 20)
        - Kevorkian, 1996 (Box 20)
        - Quinlan
          - 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 20)
          - 1985 (Box 21)
        - Socially-Assisted Dying: Media, Money & Meaning (Conference Transcript), 1997 (Box 21)
        - Television Coverage, 1976-1988 (Box 21)
        - University of Detroit Symposium, 1998 (Box 21)
      - Evidence
        - undated, 2 folders (Box 21)
        - 1965 (Box 21)
        - 1968, undated (Box 21)
        - Hearsay, 1964 (Box 21)
      - Exclusionary Rule
        - undated (Box 21)
        - "The Crime Crisis and Proposed Procedural Reform,", undated (Box 21)
        - Mapp v. Ohio, undated (Box 21)
        - "Reply to Critics of the Exclusionary Rule,", 1978 (Box 21)
      - False Pretenses, undated (Box 21)
      - Federal Jurisdiction, undated (Box 21)
      - Felony Murder, 1977; undated; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Fifth Amendment, undated (Box 22)
      - Homicide, undated (Box 22)
      - Insanity, 1972-1975; 1983; 1998; undated; 5 folders (Box 22)
      - Interrogation, 1964 (Box 22)
      - Mercy-Killing Legislation, 1976-1977 (Box 22)
      - Miranda
        - 1966-1999, undated; 3 folders (Box 22)
        - Case, 1965 (Box 22)
        - Confessions, undated (Box 22)
        - Warnings (Dickerson v. U.S.), 2000 (Box 22)
        - Welch, Robert C., 1983 (Box 22)
      - Necessity, 1963; undated; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Omissions and Causation, undated (Box 23)
      - Provocation, 1998; undated (Box 23)
      - Provocation and Necessity, undated (Box 23)
      - Punishment, undated (Box 23)
      - Search and Seizure, 1997 (Box 23)
      - Self Defense and Deadly Force, undated (Box 23)
      - Race Riots
        - 1967, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - Clippings
          - 1967, 2 folders (Box 23)
          - 1967-1971, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - Panel Discussions regarding Detroit, 1967 (Box 23)
    - Videocassettes
      - Last Class, 2003 (Box 23)
      - Miranda Class, 2003 (Box 23)
  - Criminal Proceedings (Box 24)
    - undated, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 24)
    - 1998-2001 (Box 24)
- Teaching Material
  - Miscellaneous
    - Constitutional Law, 1966 (Box 28)
    - Faculty Activities Record, 1966 (Box 28)
    - Final Exams, 1962-1964 (Box 28)
    - Recommendations, 1965-1971 (Box 28)
    - Seminar Papers (Box 28)
- Writings, 0.7 linear feet
  The Writings series (.7 linear feet) includes drafts of articles written by Kamisar. This series is arranged chronologically by date of publication, with undated articles arranged alphabetically by title and located at the beginning of the series. Kamisar's 1958 work "Some Non-Religious Views Against Proposed 'Mercy-Killing' Legislation" is located in this series. In 1973, this article was reprinted, with a new forward, and retitled "Euthanasia: A Practical View." There are also several pieces on criminal law such as the 1967 Supplement to Modern Criminal Procedure...and Basic Criminal Procedure as well as several articles on the Exclusionary rule and Miranda rights. The series also includes studies on police interrogation, discussions of Gideon v. Wainwright on the decision's twenty-fifth anniversary, an analysis of the make-up of the Supreme Court, and two book reviews written by Kamisar.
  Drafts of writings and reprints are located throughout the Research Topical Files. In addition, researchers should consult the Michigan Law Review for Kamisar articles published there. Volume 99, issue 5 of the Michigan Law Review is dedicated to Kamisar. For more comprehensive bibliographies of Kamisar publications, researchers should consult the folder title "Bibliography" and "Publications" under the heading "Biography" located in box 2.
  - Articles
    - "The Fourth Amendment Exclusionary Rule,", undated (Box 24)
    - "'Necessity' and 'Coercion': An Exercise in What is and What Ought to be Criminal Behavior,", undated (Box 24)
    - "Foreword: The School Desegregation Case in Retrospect-Some Reflections on Causes and Effects,", undated (Box 24)
    - "The Search and Seizure of America,", undated (Box 24)
    - "The Warren Court (Was it Really so Defense-Minded?), the Burger Court (Is it Really so Prosecution-Oriented?) and Police Investigatory Practices,", undated (Box 24)
    - "Some Non-Religious Views Against Proposed 'Mercy-Killing' Legislation,", 1958 (Box 24)
    - "1967 Supplement to Modern Criminal Procedure...and Basic Criminal Procedure...," (Box 24)
    - "We Continue to Talk Big But Think Small,", 1967 (Box 24)
    - "How to Use, Abuse-And Fight Back With-Crime Statistics,", 1972 (Box 24)
    - "Euthanasia: A Practical View,", 1973 (Box 24)
    - "Does (Did) (Should) the Exclusionary Rule Rest on a 'Principled Basis' Rather Than an 'Empirical Proposition'?,", 1983 (Box 24)
    - "Police Interrogation and Confessions,", 1983 (Box 24)
    - " Gideon v. Wainwright A Quarter-Century Later,", 1990 (Box 24)
    - "Is Constitutional Law 'the Expression of Chance'?,", 1990 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous Articles regarding the Souter Appointment to the Supreme Court, 1990 (Box 24)
    - "Do Law-and-Order Advocates Really Want a 'Strict Constructionist',", 1990 (Box 24)
    - "Don't Eat the Poison Fruit,", 2003 (Box 24)
    - "Losing Liberty: Due Process,", 2003 (Box 24)
    - "Gideon's Unkept Promise,", 2003 (Box 24)
  - Reviews and Miscellaneous
    - "Hugo Black,", 1977 (Box 24)
    - "Practical Reasons and Reasonable Practice,", 1994 (Box 24)
    - "Constitutional Law: Cases, Comments and Questions", 1964 (Box 28)
    - "Criminal Justice in Our Time" (Box 28)
    - Reprint Requests, 1962-1965 (Box 28)
    - "Was Justice Done in the Algiers Motel Incident?", 1970 (Box 28)
    - Writing Requests, 1964-1966 (Box 28)
Related Material
Other Law School and related collections include:
University of Michigan. Law School. Records
University of Michigan Law School. Publications
University of Michigan. Law School. Oral History Interviews.
Michigan Law Review
In addition, there are numerous personal collections of Law School faculty housed at the Bentley Historical Library.